<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
  <!-- Fill in your name for FIRSTNAME and SURNAME. -->
  <!ENTITY dhfirstname "halfdog">
  <!ENTITY dhsurname   "">
  <!-- dhusername could also be set to "&dhfirstname; &dhsurname;". -->
  <!ENTITY dhusername  "halfdog">
  <!ENTITY dhemail     "me@halfdog.net">
  <!-- SECTION should be 1-8, maybe w/ subsection other parameters are
       allowed: see man(7), man(1) and
       http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Man-Page/q2.html. -->
  <!ENTITY dhsection   "1">
  <!-- TITLE should be something like "User commands" or similar (see
       http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Man-Page/q2.html). -->
  <!ENTITY dhtitle     "StorageTool User Manual">
  <!ENTITY dhucpackage "STORAGETOOL">
  <!ENTITY dhpackage   "guerillabackup">
]>

<refentry>
  <refentryinfo>
    <title>&dhtitle;</title>
    <productname>&dhpackage;</productname>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
       <firstname>&dhfirstname;</firstname>
        <surname>&dhsurname;</surname>
        <contrib>Wrote this manual page.</contrib>
        <address>
          <email>&dhemail;</email>
        </address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <copyright>
      <year>2022</year>
      <holder>&dhusername;</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>This manual page was written for guerillabackup system
        on Linux systems, e.g. Debian.</para>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
        document under the terms of the Lesser GNU General Public
        License, Version 3.</para>
      <para>On Debian systems, the complete text of the Lesser
        GNU General Public License can be found in
        <filename>/usr/share/common-licenses/LGPL-3</filename>.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </refentryinfo>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>STORAGETOOL</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>&dhsection;</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>StorageTool</refname>
    <refpurpose>Manage guerillabackup backup data storages</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>StorageTool</command>
      <!-- These are several examples, how syntaxes could look -->
      <arg choice="plain">
        <option>--Config <replaceable>file</replaceable></option>
        <option>--DryRun</option>
      </arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1 id="description">
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>This is the manual page for the <command>StorageTool</command>
      command. The tool is used to perform operations on backup
      file storage locations as used by <command>BackupGenerator</command>
      or <command>TransferService</command> to store backup data.</para>
    <para>Currently the tool supports checking storage file naming
    to identify incomplete backups due to aborts during backup
    generation or transfer e.g. by reboots or crashes. To ignore
    files for a reason, e.g. notes, add entries to the status
    file, e.g.</para>

    <para>For all files defining valid backup data elements,
    configurable policies are applied. See POLICIES section below
    for supported policies.</para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="options">
    <title>OPTIONS</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--Config <replaceable>file</replaceable></option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This optional parameter specifies an alternative
          configuration file instead of /etc/guerillabackup/storage-tool-config.json.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>--DryRun</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This optional parameter will make StorageTool
          perform policy checks only but will not modify the
          storage, e.g. by deleting files flagged for deletion
          by a retention policy.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="policies">
    <title>POLICIES</title>
    <para>StorageTool can apply multiple policies to each backup
    data source but it is only possible to have one policy of
    a given type (see policy types below). Which policies to
    apply is defined by the StorageTool configuration file "Policies"
    parameter. A regular expression is used to select which sources
    policies should be applied to with the first matching expression
    taking precedence. For each regular expression a list of
    polices with parameters is defined. See
    /data/etc/storage-tool-config.json.template for examples.</para>

    <para>To ease policy selection in large setups, policy inheritance
    can be used. A included configuration (see "Include" configuration
    parameter) may also define policies, which can extend or
    override the policies from the parent configuration(s) when
    they have a higher priority. To disable policy inheritance
    a subconfiguration may add a "null" policy as first entry
    in the Policy list.</para>

    <para>Each policy defined in the StorageTool configuration
    file may also keep policy status information in the status
    file. The status data is usually updated as the policy is
    applied unless there is a significant policy violation. That
    will require the user either to fix the root cause of the
    violation (e.g. backup data was found to be missing) or the
    user may update the status to ignore the violation. The later
    cannot be done interactively via StorageTool yet, one has
    to adjust the storage status configuration manually. Therefore
    the user has to create or update the status configuration
    with the the backup element name (the filename relative to
    the data directory without any suffix) as key and the status
    information for the policy as described below (and sometimes
    given as hint on the console too).</para>

    <para>StorageTool supports following policies:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">Interval:</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify that all sources generate backups at expected
          rates and all backups were transferred successfully.
          Thus this policy eases spotting of system failures
          in the backup system. An example policy configuration
          is:</para>

          <programlisting>
...
  "Policies": [
    {
      "Sources": "^(.*/)?root$",
      "List": [
        {
          "Name": "Interval",
          "Priority": 100,
          "FullMin": "6d20H",
          "FullMax": "6d28H",
          "IncMin": "20H",
          "IncMax": "28H"
        }, {
...</programlisting>

          <para>This configuration specifies that to all backups
          from source with name "root" (the default backup created
          by the <command>BackupGenerator</command>) an Interval
          policy shall be epplied. The policy will expect full
          backups every 7 days +- 4 hours and incremental backups
          each day +- 4 hours.</para>

          <para>When policy validation fails for a given source,
          the policy configuration may be adjusted but also the
          violation may be ignored by updating the check status.
          Thus the validation error will not be reported any
          more in the next run. The status data in that case
          may look like:</para>

          <programlisting>
...
  "20200102000000-root-full": {
    "Interval": {
      "Ignore": "both"
    }
  },
...</programlisting>

          <para>This status indicates, that the both interval
          checks for the interval from the previous full and
          incremental backup to the backup named above should
          be disabled. Do disable only one type of checks, the
          "full" or "inc" type keyword is used instead of "both".</para>

          <para>While above is fine to ignore singular policy
          violations, also the policy itself may be adjusted.
          This is useful when e.g. the backup generation intervals
          where changed at the source. The status data in that
          case could look like:</para>

          <programlisting>
...
  "20200102000000-root-full": {
    "Interval": {
      "Config": {
        "FullMax": "29d28H",
        "FullMin": "29d20H",
        "IncMax": "6d28H",
        "IncMin": "6d20H"
      }
    }
  },
...</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B">LevelRetention:</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This defines a retention policy defined by retention
          levels, e.g. on first level keep each backup for 30
          days, next level keep 12 weekly backups, on the next
          level keep 12 monthly backups, then 12 every three
          month and from that on only yearly ones.</para>

          <programlisting>
...
  "Policies": [
    {
      "Sources": "^(.*/)?root$",
      "List": [
        {
          "Name": "LevelRetention",
          "Levels": [
# Keep weekly backups for 30 days, including incremental backups.
            {
              "KeepCount": 30,
              "Interval": "day",
              "TimeRef": "latest",
              "KeepInc": true
            },
# Keep weekly backups for 3 month, approx. 13 backups.
            {
              "KeepCount": 13,
              "Interval": "day",
              "AlignModulus": 7
            },
...
            {
              "KeepCount": 12,
              "Interval": "month",
              "AlignModulus": 3,
              "AlignValue": 1
            },
...</programlisting>

          <para>This configuration defines, that on the finest
          level, backups for 30 days should be kept counting
          from the most recent on ("TimeRef": "latest"), including
          incremental backups ("KeepInc": true). Thus for machines
          not producing backups any more, the most recent ones
          are kept uncoditionally.</para>

          <para>On the next level, 13 weekly backups are kept,
          while may overlap with backups already kept due to
          the first level configuration from above. But here
          only full backups will be kept, that were generated
          after every 7th day due to "AlignModulus", prefering
          the one generated on day 0.</para>

          <para>At another level, only one backup is kept every
          three month, prefering the one from the month numbered
          1, 4, 7, 10 due to "AlignModulus" and "AlignValue".
          Hence the first backup in January, April, ... should
          be kept.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="files">
    <title>FILES</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>/etc/guerillabackup/storage-tool-config.json</filename></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The default configuration file for StorageTool
          tool. Use storage-tool-config.json.template to create
          it. The template also contains the documentation for
          each available parameter. The most relevant parameters
          for <command>StorageTool</command> are DataDir, Include
          and Status.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>/var/lib/guerillabackup/state/storage-tool-status.json</filename></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>This is the recommended location for the toplevel
          StorageTool status file. The file has to contain valid
          JSON data but also comment lines starting with #. See
          POLICIES section above for description of policy specific
          status data.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="bugs">
    <title>BUGS</title>
    <para>
      For guerillabackup setups installed from packages, e.g.
      .deb or .rpm files usually installed via package management
      software, e.g. apt-get, aptitude, rpm, yast, please report
      bugs to the package maintainer.</para>
    <para>
      For setups from unpackaged software trunk, please report
      at <ulink url="https://github.com/halfdog/guerillabackup/issues"/>.</para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="see_also">
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
<!-- In alpabetical order. -->
    <para>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>TransferService</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
